<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<events_and_full-text>
   <allPainEvents doc-name="Libation Bearers">
      <pain xml:id="pain_1">
         <painStart rec="Orestes" recGen="man" recNorm="yes" painType="both"/>now that I have come to this
						land and returned from exile. On this mounded grave I cry out to my father
						to hearken, to hear me<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_2">
         <painStart rec="Electra" recGen="woman" recNorm="yes" painType="em"/>I think my own sister Electra is
						approaching, distinguished by her bitter grief<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_3">
         <painStart rec="Chorus" recGen="woman" recNorm="yes" painType="both"/>My cheek is marked with bloody gashes
							where my nails have cut fresh furrows. And yet through all my life my
							heart is fed with lamentation. Rips are torn by my griefs through the
							linen web of my garment, torn in the cloth that covers my breast, the
							cloth of robes struck for the sake of my mirthless
							misfortunes.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_4">
         <painStart rec="Chorus"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="master"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>O mother Earth, she sends me forth,
							godless woman that she is. But I am afraid to utter the words she
							charged me to speak. For what atonement is there for blood fallen to
							earth? Ah, hearth of utter grief! Ah, house laid low in ruin! Sunless
							darkness, loathed by men, enshrouds our house due to the death of its
							master.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_5">
         <painStart rec="Chorus"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="slave"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="master"
                    direct="yes"/>it is fitting for me to govern my bitter hate, even
							against my will, and submit to the wishes of my masters, whether just or
							unjust.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_6">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>Shall I
						say that I bring these offerings to a loved husband from a loving wife—from
						my own mother? I do not have the assurance for that, nor do I know what I
						should say as I pour this libation onto my father's tomb. Or shall I speak
						the words that men are accustomed to use: “To those who send these honors
						may he return benefits”—a gift, indeed, to match their evil?<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_7">
         <painStart rec="Orestes-and-Electra"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="children"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>For now we are bartered
						away like vagrants by her who bore us<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_8">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>who in exchange got as her mate Aegisthus, who was her
						accomplice in your murder<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_9">
         <painStart rec="Orestes"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="son"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>Orestes is an outcast from his inheritance, while they
						in their insolence revel openly in the winnings of your toil. But that
						Orestes may come home with good fortune I pray to you, father: Oh, hearken
						to me! And as for myself, grant that I may prove far more circumspect than
						my mother and more reverent in deed.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_10">
         <painStart rec="Electra" recGen="woman" recNorm="yes" painType="em"/>Over my
						heart, too, there sweeps a surge of bitterness, and I am struck as if a
						sword had run me through<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_11">
         <painStart rec="Orestes-and-Electra"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="children"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>Nor yet in truth did she clip it from her head, the
						murderess, my own mother,who has assumed a godless spirit regarding her
						children that ill accords with the name of mother<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_12">
         <painStart rec="Orestes-and-Electra"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="children"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="no"/>Behold
						the orphaned brood of a father eagle that perished in the meshes, in the
						coils of a fierce viper. They are utterly orphaned, gripped by the famine of
						hunger: for they are not grown to full strength to bring their father's
						quarry to the nest. So you see both me and poor Electra here, children
						bereft of their father, both outcasts alike from our home<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_13">
         <painStart rec="society"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="subjects"
                    inf="Clytaemestra-and-Aegisthus"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="ruler"
                    direct="yes"/>my keen grief for my father, and also the pinch of
						poverty—that my countrymen, the most renowned of mortals, who overthrew
							
						in the spirit of glory, should not be subjected so to a pair of
						women<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_14">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>The
							murdered man has his dirge; the guilty man is revealed.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_15">
         <painStart rec="Orestes-and-Electra"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="children"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="no"/>your two children mourn you in a dirge
							over your tomb. As suppliants and exiles as well they have sought a
							haven at your sepulchre. What of these things is good, what free of
							evil? Is it not hopeless to wrestle against doom?<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_16">
         <painStart rec="Orestes-and-Electra"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="children"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="no"/>if only beneath
								's walls you had been slain, slashed by some
							Lycian spearman! Then you would have left a good name for your children
							in their halls, and in their maturity you would have made their lives
							admired by men. And in a land beyond the sea you would have found a tomb
							heaped high with earth, no heavy burden for your house to
							bear—<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_17">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>I wish
							rather that his murderers had been killed by their own loved ones, just
							as they killed you<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_18">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra-and-Aegisthus"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"/>May it be mine to raise a hearty shout in triumph
							over the man when he is stabbed and over the woman as she perishes!<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_19">
         <painStart rec="Chorus"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="slave"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="master"
                    direct="no"/>Why should I try to keep hidden what nevertheless
							hovers before my soul? Full against the prow of my heart wrath blows
							sharply in rancorous hate.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_20">
         <painStart rec="Chorus" recGen="woman" recNorm="yes" painType="em"/>But
							again my heart throbs as I hear this pitiful lament. At once I am devoid
							of hope and my viscera are darkened at the words I hear.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_21">
         <painStart rec="Orestes-and-Electra"
                    recGen="mix"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="children"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>To what could we more fittingly appeal
							than to those very miseries we have endured from the woman herself who
							bore us?<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_22">
         <painStart rec="Chorus" recGen="woman" recNorm="yes" painType="phys"/>till my battered and wretched head
							resounded with the strokes.Away with you, cruel and utterly brazen mother! </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_23">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="no"/>You dared to give your husband a most cruel burial:
							unmourned, without lamentation, a king unattended by his
							people.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_24">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="no"/>Yet
							with the help of the gods, and with the help of my own hands, will she
							not atone for the dishonor she did my father?<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_25">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="mother"
                    inf="Orestes"
                    infGen="man"
                    infNorm="yes"
                    infRel="son"
                    direct="yes"/>Let me only take her life, then let me
							die!<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_26">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>he was brutally mangled.
							And even as she buried him in this way, she acted with intent to make
							the manner of his death<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_27">
         <painStart rec="Electra"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="daughter"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="no"/>But
							all the while I was kept sequestered, despised, accounted a worthless
							thing.Kennelled in my room as if I were a vicious cur, I gave free vent
							to my streaming tears, which came more readily than laughter, as in my
							concealment I poured out my lament in plentiful weeping<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_28">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>O father, who perished by a death unbefitting a
						king<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_29">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>Father, remember the bath where you were robbed of life.
					 And remember how they devised a strange net to cast about you. You were caught, my father, in fetters forged by no smith's hand.And in a fabric shamefully devised.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_30">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra" recGen="woman" recNorm="no" painType="em"/>she was
						shaken by dreams and wandering terrors of the night that she sent these
						offerings<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_31">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra" recGen="woman" recNorm="no" painType="phys"/>No: it drew in clotted blood with the milk.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_32">
         <painStart rec="Aegisthus"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="stepfather"
                    inf="Orestes"
                    infGen="man"
                    infNorm="yes"
                    infRel="stepson"
                    direct="yes"/>I will skewer him with my swift sword
						and lay him dead.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_33">
         <painStart rec="Thesius-grandchild"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="son"
                    inf="Thesius-daughter"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>she destroyed her own child by burning
							the charred brand of the same age as he when, coming from his mother's
							womb, he cried out, and it aged in pace with him through his lifeto the
							day decreed by fate.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_34">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>it is the right time to tell of a marriage void of
							love, an abomination to the house,and the plots devised by a wife's
							cunning against her warrior lord, against her lord revered with reason
							by his foes.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_35">
         <painStart rec="Nurse" recGen="woman" recNorm="yes" painType="em"/>Miserable woman that I am! How the old unbearable troubles of every sort
						that occurred in this house of Atreushave always made my heart ache within
						my breast! But never yet have I endured a blow like this. For all the other
						troubles I bore patiently, but my beloved Orestes, on whom I spent my soul,
						whom I took from his mother at birth and nursed, and the many and
						troublesome tasks, fruitless for all my enduring them, when his loud and
						urgent cries broke my rest....<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_36">
         <painStart rec="Aegisthus"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="stepfather"
                    inf="Orestes"
                    infGen="man"
                    infNorm="yes"
                    infRel="stepson"
                    direct="yes"/>My master is slain! O woe! I cry yet
						again, for the third time. Aegisthus is no more!<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_37">
         <painStart rec="Aegisthus"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="stepfather"
                    inf="Orestes"
                    infGen="man"
                    infNorm="yes"
                    infRel="stepson"
                    direct="yes"/>My beloved, valiant Aegisthus! You are dead! You love this man? Then you will lie in the same grave, and you will never
						abandon him in death.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_38">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="mother"
                    inf="Orestes"
                    infGen="man"
                    infNorm="yes"
                    infRel="son"
                    direct="yes"/>I mean to kill you by his very side.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_39">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>Murder my father and then make your home with
						me?<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_40">
         <painStart rec="Orestes"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="son"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>You brought me to birth and yet you cast me out to
						misery.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_41">
         <painStart rec="Orestes"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="son"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="mother"
                    direct="yes"/>I was sold in disgrace, though I was born of a free
						father.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_42">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra" recGen="woman" recNorm="no" painType="em"/>It
						is a grief for women to be deprived of a husband, my child.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_43">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>You killed him whom you should not<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_44">
         <painStart rec="Clytaemestra"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="no"
                    painType="phys"
                    recRel="mother"
                    inf="Orestes"
                    infGen="man"
                    infNorm="yes"
                    infRel="son"
                    direct="yes"/>so suffer what should not be.<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_45">
         <painStart rec="Chorus"
                    recGen="woman"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="em"
                    recRel="slave"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="master"
                    direct="no"/>and I am freed from the
							cruel curb that restrained our household<painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_46">
         <painStart rec="Agamemnon"
                    recGen="man"
                    recNorm="yes"
                    painType="both"
                    recRel="husband"
                    inf="Clytaemestra"
                    infGen="woman"
                    infNorm="no"
                    infRel="wife"
                    direct="yes"/>Behold this pair, oppressors of the land, who murdered my
						father and ransacked my house! <painEnd/>
      </pain>
      <pain xml:id="pain_47">
         <painStart rec="society" recGen="mix" recNorm="yes" painType="both"/>First, at the beginning, came the cruel
						woes of children slain for food; next, the fate of a man, a king,when the
						warlord of the Achaeans perished, murdered in his bath. And now, once again,
						there has come from somewhere a third, a deliverer, or shall I say a doom?
						Oh when will it finish its work, when will the fury of calamity, lulled to
						rest, find an end and cease?<painEnd/>
      </pain>
   </allPainEvents>
   <tragedyText>
      <body>
         <div1 type="episode" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <stage>The tomb of Agamemnon. Enter Orestes and Pylades</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orestes</speaker>
               <p>Hermes of the nether world, you who guard the powers that are your father's,
						prove yourself my savior and ally, I entreat you, <mappedPain xml:id="tragedy_2"/>